Guide to the Jesse Pyrant Andrews photographs, 1973-2012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
- View from Amtrak Northeast Regional, Train #147, Train Project Series, 2010, (31 prints)
  - [Overhead view of tree-lined tracks], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_082)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_108_36
  - [Worker on railroad bridge with street beyond], 2012 Mar. 23 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_083)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_19A_20
  - [City station ramp with fence, opaque roof with arches], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_084)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_109_5_A
  - [Large covered train station platform with white stool], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_085)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_109_14_A
  - [Reflection of photographer's face on interior train window], 2010 Nov. 19 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_086)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_111_20_A_21
- Virginia Photographs Series, 1976-2008 and undated, (24 prints)
  Comprises 24 11x14 inch black-and-white gelatin silver prints, primarily portraits of farmers and disabled veterans taken in the Halifax, Virginia area. There is one oral history accompanying a print of veteran Frank Joseph Wilcoski. Arranged in original order as received. Information in brackets is supplied by library staff; original identification codes and titles assigned by the photographer are retained.
  [The oral history is available in mp3 file format. Please contact a reference archivist for access.]
  - Reid Carter, Chatham, Va., 1976 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_087)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_52_6
    Reid Carter was a mechanic who worked primarily on pulpwood trucks. He lived with his mother in a cabin without running water or electricity. When she died in 1982, at age 100, Reid lost his mind and was committed to a state mental institution in Staunton. He died a few months later.
  - Tattoo Red's, Danville, Va., 1994 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_088)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_87_17
    Red's was a gathering place for local outlaw bikers, the Scorpions. Red died in 2007.
  - Lily Savage, Halifax, Va., 2007 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_089)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_97_25
  - Halifax County, Va., 2008 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_090)
  - Edwin Wemple, Charlottesville, Va., 1976 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_091)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_4x5_3
    Ed Wemple grew up in Charlottesville and graduated from the University of Virginia. He wandered the country during the depression of the 1930s. He worked as a longshoreman in New York, in lumber camps in Oregon and eventually went to Mexico, where he became a heroin addict. He cured himself by walking from El Paso to the Oklahoma border. He returned to New York, where he lived until 1964, taking in the bohemian and jazz cultures and working at odd jobs. He returned to Charlottesville in 1964 and lived there until his death in 1987. I lived in the same house with him for a year. He had not had a bath in nine years and spent his time reading and sleeping. He went by taxi once a week to the Alderman Library to replenish his book supply. A wonderful man who had endless stories to tell about his life. I regret that I did not record any of our conversations.
  - Frank Joseph Wilcoski and his son, Frank Joseph Wilcoski, Jr., 2005 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_092)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_146_53
    This print measures 9 7/8 x 7 7/8". Oral history recording accompanies this print and is available in mp3 format; contact the Rubenstein Library for access information. Part of the Carter-Wooding project.
  - Matthew Lafayette Aaron ("Fate" Aaron), undated (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_093)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_77_19
    Born Jan. 10, 1919 at Callands, Va. Grew up on a tobacco farm, enlisted in the Army in 1941, fought as an infantryman through North Africa, then as a Ranger through the Sicilian and Italian campaigns. Discharged November, 1945. Wounded three times in what he called "three years of continuous combat." As a Ranger he was usually at the forward most front of the fighting. He has suffered since his discharge with severe PTSD and alcoholism. In spite of that, as well as his physical wounds, he was a successful tobacco farmer until he retired in 1994. He lives on the same farm where he was born. Up to this time I have not been able to convince Mr. Aaron to agree to an oral history. When I made this photograph, he said, "I was a nice fellow when this picture was made (the portrait of himself he is holding), before I went overseas. Since then, I don't know, I just never have been the same." This is part of the Disabled Veterans series.
  - Mrs. Maynard Amos, undated (Box 4, Image 3, Image RL10010_P_094)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_51_35
    Mrs. Maynard Amos operated Amos' General Store at Callands, Va. with her husband until he suffered a stroke in 1999. Since then she has run the store on her own. One of only a handful of such rural businesses still in operation, it remains a gathering place for local farmers and a source for gasoline, farm supplies, groceries, patent medicines, and just about anything else a person might need.
  - Giles Herman Motley ("Mud" Motley), 1961_2003, near Climax, Va., August 1998 (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_095)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_41_16
    Died of alcoholism, Oct., 2003. A close friend.
  - Giles Herman Motley at Weal, VA., 2002 October (Box 4, Image RL10010_P_096)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_49_28
  - James Bianchi, sandwich maker, at the Corner Deli, Charlottesville, Va., 1976 September (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_097)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_38_28
  - Rogers Royal holding a stick of cured bright leaf tobacco, near Climax, Va. (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_098)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_49_19
    He is the last farmer in Pittsylvania county to cure his tobacco with wood. This is practically a lost art, having been replaced almost completely with oil and propane curing by the mid 1970s.
  - Rogers Royal sitting under a tobacco curing barn shelter at his farm, October, 2000 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_099)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_49_22
    Born on this farm in 1930, one of sixteen children. His father was killed in a fall from a hay wagon in 1951.
  - Lawrence Van Witcher (Larry Witcher), 1950_2004, Tomahawk Mill near Climax, Va., July, 1984 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_100)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_56_8LW
    Larry was the miller at this water_powered grist mill, which had been in continuous operation since the 1870s. He died in 2004 from a heart attack. A lifelong friend.
  - George Riser, Covesville, Va., 2005 Jan. 1 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_101)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_40_13
  - Parlor dance, Carter farm, Halifax, Va., May, 2006 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_102)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_148_15
    Part of the Carter-Wooding project.
  - Parlor dance, Carter farm, Halifax, Va., May, 2006 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_103)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_147_10
    Musicians are Glenn Waller, Tim Peade, Ken Peade, and Robert Anderson. The child dancing is Mark Aaron. Carter-Wooding project.
  - Chatham Theater, Chatham, Va., 1976 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_104)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_44_22
  - Storefront, Brookneal, Va., March, 2006 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_105)
  - Storefront, Brookneal, Va., March, 2006 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_106)
  - Storefront, Brookneal, Va., March, 2006 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_107)
  - Frank H. Andrews, Chatham, Va., May, 2004 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_108)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_100_27
    Part of the Disabled Veterans Project.
  - Farm auction, Grit, Va., September, 1976 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_109)
    Orig. print number: JA_SALES_7_25
    This is the McFarland farm. They had become physically unable to continue farming.
  - William Haskell Egan, Charlottesville, Va., 1976 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_110)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_4x5_15
- Other Prints, 1973-2010, (27 prints)
  Twenty-seven 11x14 inch black-and-white images taken in New York State, California, North Carolina, and Massachusetts of street scenes, buildings, and individuals. In addition to documentary images, there are several abstract images of plants, as well as a few of houses in unidentified locations, and one of ice on a pond. Arranged in chronological order. Several prints are unnumbered. Information in brackets is supplied by library staff; original identification codes and titles assigned by the photographer are retained.
  - Street scene, Boston, Mass. with sleeping man, 1973 June (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_111)
    Unnumbered.
  - Street scene, Boston, Mass., 1973 Oct. (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_112)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_44_27
  - Broadway Hand, Cambridge, Mass., 1974 Apr. (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_113)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_44_4A
  - North End, Boston, Mass., 1974 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_114)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_40_9
    This woman operated a tiny bakery with the help of her son in the Italian section of Boston. They made marzipan, cannolis, and other pastries, as well as several kinds of bread, all wonderful.
  - Boston, Mass., 1974 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_144)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_121_5A. Elderly woman standing in front of a store holding a tract titled "AWAKE."
  - Boston, Mass., 1974 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_145)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_4_34. Children playing in the courtyard of an apartment building.
  - Boston, Mass., 1975 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_146)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_44_5A. Clothesline with clothes hanging on it, with a garden beneath.
  - David Crowder, near Crossville, Tn. [Tennessee], 1977 Aug. (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_115)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_40_33
    He picked me up hitchhiking.
  - Fox and Willie May Hold, near Crossville, Tn., 1977 Aug. (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_116)
  - Crystal Graber, Ontario, Cal., 1992 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_117)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_88_21_A
  - Helen Marshall at Forest Home, Blanch, N.C., 1997 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_118)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_4x5_24
  - Terry Moore in his firefighter's gear, 2001 May (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_119)
    Orig. print number: JA_13MCB_109_XX
  - Charlottesville, Va., 2001 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_148)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_21_14. Man walking across a parking lot, seen through partially opened curtains.
  - Abandoned grist mill, Riceville, Va., 2001 (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_149)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_35_7. Wooden building with the window closed in with a sign reading "FIN."
  - Holly Hernandsen, Pelham, N.C., 2002 Oct. (Box 5, Image RL10010_P_120)
    Orig. print number: JA_POR_3_49
  - Times Square, New York City, 2003 July (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_121)
  - Street preacher, New York City, 2003 July (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_122)
  - Kudzu house, 2003 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_123)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_58_4
  - Plant shadow, 2003 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_124)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_59_16
  - Adam's needle (yucca plant), 2003 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_125)
    Orig. print number: JA_NAT_4x5_16
  - New York City, 2003 July (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_126)
  - 45th St. at Broadway, New York, 2004 Dec. (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_127)
  - Plant shadow, 2004 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_128)
  - Storefront, 7th Avenue, New York City, December, 2004 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_129)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_78_31
  - Pond ice, 2007 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_130)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_106_53
  - New homes for sale, 2007 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_131)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_77_15
  - Danville, Va., 2010 (Box 6, Image RL10010_P_147)
    Orig. print number: JA_LAL_97_16. Storefront with the painted image of a bearded black man. Sign reading "Sanctuary."